Finding Aid for Soundings Records 1977-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Soundings records 1977-1998, 1980-1994
Soundings (Organization)
6 linear feet
Ann Arbor, Michigan, women's center founded in 1977 to help women cope with adjusting to life after widowhood or divorce. Soundings' main focus has been on job readiness, but it has offered workshops, programs, and individual and group counseling sessions on such topics as reentry into the workforce, assertiveness training, personal finance, and physical and emotional health and well-being. Records include background and history materials, administration, board of directors, grants and fundraising activities, finances, and audiovisual materials. Also includes the records of the Domestic Violence Project, Inc., a separate agency.
0151 Bj 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group (donor no. 8959 ) was received from Judy Holzchuh of Soundings in May and October 2000.
The record group is open for research.
Soundings was founded in 1977 by Glenora "Gerry" Brown in order to help women in their middle years regain their footing after widowhood or divorce. This social problem was just beginning to be recognized with the term "displaced homemaker," and there were few if any social programs in place to address the issue. Formerly a librarian at the Kelsey Library of the University of Michigan, Brown returned to school and received her Masters degree in social work. She chose to name her organization "Soundings" as a way to express the double meaning of taking a sounding on a river channel in order to navigate, and for the "sounds" all around, which a person in trouble may need help hearing through support and guidance from others. Since its beginning, Soundings' guiding mission has been to "promote both the economic and emotional well being of women." ("A Brief History of Soundings," History ("Herstory"), Printed Materials, Background, Box 1, Soundings.)
Brown first ran Soundings from her home and financed the organization with a small personal bequest. She was soon introduced to Esther Donahue, an intern at the Center for the Education of Women (CEW). Esther became the agency's assistant director from 1978 through 1987 and later, comptroller. The first big program the two partners staged was "Anchors and Options" in September of 1978 at Bach Elementary School. This session covered the topics of physical and mental well-being, assertiveness training, financial planning, and strategies for reentering the work force. Over one hundred women showed up, far exceeding their expectations for attendance.
After the Anchors and Options program, Soundings began to grow. Two local counselors volunteered their services. With startup grants received from the Ann Arbor Area Foundation and the Power Foundation, Soundings was able to pay the counselors and hire a part-time administrative assistant. A grant from the Michigan Department of Labor enabled Soundings to start its cornerstone program, "Target: Jobs for Women." Other grants came from the City of Ann Arbor and the Washtenaw County Department of Social Services. Another major Soundings program has been "Divorce and Beyond," a series of workshops and small group counseling sessions. In addition to grants and donations, Soundings is funded by program fees, which are charged on a sliding scale based on participants' income levels.
Gerry Brown retired as director of Soundings in 1986. She was succeeded as executive director by Lynne Carbeck, with Lin Orrin and others following.
As society changed over the intervening years and funding priorities shifted, Soundings faced increasing difficulty in securing sufficient operating funds for all of its programs. In addition, other existing agencies offered similar services, and women were as a whole becoming better equipped to deal with the problems accompanying divorce and widowhood. In the early 1980s, Soundings broadened its focus to include all women, not just those in their middle years.
Over the next decade, more changes to the organization took place. Soundings' initial focus was on job readiness because this had been the only area for which funding was then available. In the mid to late 1990s, Soundings endeavored to add other programs to meet the needs of changing times. Soundings also made efforts to forge alliances with national and local agencies. These attempts met with varying degrees of success. In order to increase the scope of its mission and to widen its funding base, Soundings sought acceptance as a United Way member agency, explored alignment with Washtenaw Community College, and participated in a pilot project with Michigan Rehabilitation Services and the Department of Social Services. Soundings continues to provide support and services to women in the Washtenaw County area.
The collection is divided into seven series: Background, Administrative, Domestic Violence Project, Board of Directors, Grants and Fundraising, Financial, and Audiovisual. Types of materials and information include audio tapes and videotapes (primarily featuring interviews with Soundings staff and members), albums, photographs, slides, clippings, newsletters, annual reports, program files, client letters, workshop files, board meeting minutes, financial summaries, funding information and grant proposals, background and miscellaneous information, and files from the Domestic Violence Project, Inc. (a related agency).
Subjects:
Abused wives--Services for--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Assertiveness training--Michigan.; Career changes--Michigan.; Displaced homemakers--Services for--Michigan.; Divorced women--Michigan--Life skills guides.; Family violence--Michigan.; Soundings (Organization); Unemployed women workers--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Vocational guidance for women--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Women's shelters--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women--Employment re-entry--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Women--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Brown, Glenora W.; Domestic Violence Project, Inc.; Donahue, Esther.; Phelan, Bessie.; Safe House (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Material:
Soundings (Organization); Displaced homemakers--Michigan.; Divorced women.; Widows.; Fund raising.; Workshops (Adult education)--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Sound Recordings
Soundings (Organization); Displaced homemakers--Michigan.; Women--Michigan--Washtenaw County.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- Background
  The Background series (0.2 linear feet) consists of printed materials that provide information on the history, structure, program offerings, and accomplishments of the organization. This series contains program brochures, newspaper and magazine clippings pertaining to Soundings and related endeavors, Soundings' newsletters, incorporation papers, a file on the history of the organization, and other topical files, including material on a celebration of Soundings' tenth anniversary and a student research paper on Gerry Brown's life and her founding of the organization.
  - Brochures 1979-1993, undated (Box 1)
  - Clippings File 1978-1995 (Box 1)
    (includes a chronology and timeline through 1999)
  - Clippings 1981-1994, undated (Box 1)
  - History ("Herstory") 1977-1988 (Box 1)
  - Incorporation Papers 1977, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Joint Operating Agreement September 1986 (Box 1)
  - Letters of Support March 1988-January 1994 (Box 1)
  - Martha Hong's Paper: biography of Soundings founder Gerry Brown (Box 1)
  - Newsletters 1988-1998 (Box 1)
    (also includes flyers and announcements)
  - Soundings' 10th Anniversary 1988 (Box 1)
    (related photographs in Audiovisual series)
  - PR Sheets 1990-1994, undated (Box 1)
- Administrative
  The Administrative series (1.3 linear feet) is comprised of five subseries: Program Materials, Miscellaneous Administrative, Cooperating Organizations, Program Evaluations, and Personnel. The Program Materials subseries consists of workbooks, announcements, and some correspondence from Soundings' various job readiness and counseling programs. It is arranged alphabetically by program name. Also included in this subseries are the Participants files, with poems, letters, and quotes by participants, apparently used for promotional purposes. "Miscellaneous Administrative" contains topical files arranged alphabetically. These files relate more to Soundings' day-to-day administration than to its outreach programs. The "Cooperating Organizations" subseries is arranged alphabetically. The subseries consists of correspondence and other materials from organizations with which Soundings worked. Soundings was either a part of these organizations or received recognition or assistance from them. The Program Evaluations subseries contains evaluations of Soundings' many programs. These evaluations were filled out anonymously by the program participants. Evaluations are arranged chronologically, with an alphabetical arrangement within each year. The Personnel subseries contains contracts, evaluations, and correspondence related to the staff of Soundings.
  - Program Materials
    - Divorce Kit circa 1990-1994 (Box 1)
    - Focus Groups 1992 (Box 1)
    - Iva Wilson (Career Women's Series) March 1992-November 1993 (Box 1)
    - Jobs Project circa 1990-1994 (Box 1)
    - Incest Survival August 1991 (Box 1)
    - Menopause 1991-1993 (Box 1)
    - Music Therapy April 1994 (Box 1)
    - Next Step, 3 folders
      - Intake circa 1991-1994 (Box 1)
      - Marketing circa 1990-1992 (Box 1)
      - Next Step Notebook 1992 (Box 1)
    - Outplacement circa 1991 (Box 1)
    - Self Esteem 1994 (Box 1)
    - Sexual Assault (Box 1)
    - Sexual Harassment/Education (Box 1)
    - Single Parents 1990-1994 (Box 1)
    - Substance Abuse 1990 (Box 1)
    - Support Groups May 1993-January 1994 (Box 1)
    - Target Notebook, Original (Box 1)
    - Target 1995, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Turning Points (Sandi Cooper) (Box 1)
    - Participants, 4 folders
      - Quotes from Participants circa 1980s-1990s (Box 1)
      - Letters from Participants circa 1980s-1990s (Box 1)
      - Poems by Participants (Box 1)
      - Participant Profiles circa 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Administrative
    - Bylaws 1989 (Box 1)
    - Budgets 1990-1994 (Box 1)
      (includes some budget-related correspondence)
    - Computer Accounting Software 1989-1991 (Box 1)
    - Five-year Strategic Plan May 1990-May 1994 (Box 1)
    - Opportunities, Inc. (Career Transitions) circa 1991 (Box 1)
    - Organizational Development 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    - Policies (Box 1)
    - Presentation to Michigan Occupational Therapy Association May 20, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Program Statistics 1994 (Box 1)
      (includes miscellaneous background statistical information for 1987-1992)
    - Prospectus for Growth 1977-1978 (Box 1)
    - Resource Development Consultant circa 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - Scholarships Fall 1994, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Strategic Planning 1990 (Box 1)
    - Strategic Planning Task Force 1988-1991 (Box 1)
  - Cooperating Organizations
    - Ann Arbor Inn July 1992 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Area Chamber of Commerce June 1991-November 1992 (Box 1)
    - CEW (Center for the Education of Women) 1992 (Box 1)
    - Junior League of Ann Arbor October 1993 (Box 1)
    - NEW Center February 1993-March 1993 (Box 1)
    - NOW Feminist Achievement Award March 1988-April 1988 (Box 1)
    - Prospect Place Letter of Agreement January 1989-February 1989 (Box 1)
    - Society Bank September 1993-November 1993 (Box 1)
  - Program Evaluations
    - 1981 Reunion Evaluations September 1981 (Box 2)
    - 1984 Displaced Homemaker Survey circa 1984 (Box 2)
    - 1990
      - Career Change March 6, 1990 (Box 2)
      - Career Change May 8, 1990 (Box 2)
      - Co-dependency November 1990-December 1990 (Box 2)
      - Communication in Relationships October 1990 (Box 2)
      - Divorce and Beyond May 1990 (Box 2)
      - Divorce and Beyond August 1990-September 1990 (Box 2)
      - Family of Origin June 26, 1990-July 31, 1990 (Box 2)
      - Self Esteem June 14, 1990 (Box 2)
      - Self Esteem-Health February 27, 1990 (Box 2)
      - Self Sufficiency November 1990 (Box 2)
      - Target December 1990 (Box 2)
    - 1991
      - Career Directions May 1991 (Box 2)
      - Career Directions, Fall 1991 (Box 2)
      - Divorce and Beyond May 1991-June 1991 (Box 2)
      - Divorce and Beyond March 1991, June 1991 (Box 2)
      - Family of Origin September 1991 (Box 2)
      - Incest Recovery January 1991-April 1991 (Box 2)
      - Incest Recovery May 1991-July 1991 (Box 2)
      - Relationship Addiction May 1991 (Box 2)
      - Self Esteem May 1991 (Box 2)
      - Self Esteem-Health June 1991 (Box 2)
      - Target July 1991 (Box 2)
      - Target October 1991 (Box 2)
    - 1992
      - Target May 1992-June 1992 (Box 2)
      - Target VI August 1992 (Box 2)
      - Target VII September 1992 (Box 2)
    - 1993
      - Target March 1993 (Box 2)
      - Target November 1993 (Box 2)
      - Women's Financial Information Program November 1993 (Box 2)
    - 1994 Women's Issues Support Group, June 1994-July 1994 (Box 2)
    - 1995 Assertiveness Building, April 1995 (Box 2)
    - 1996 Lifework, October 1996 (Box 2)
      (includes program workbook)
  - Personnel: contracts, job descriptions, evaluations, and correspondence
    - Interns circa 1980s-1994, 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Contractuals 1991-1995, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Staff 1991-1995, 6 folders (Box 2)
    - "Soundings Employees Herstory": employee timeline August 1994 (Box 2)
- Domestic Violence Project:
  The Domestic Violence Project series (0.5 linear feet) consists of minutes, reports, and correspondence from the board meetings and the annual membership meetings of the organization called the Domestic Violence Project (also known as the Domestic Violence Project, Inc.). The Domestic Violence Project records were accessioned along with those of Soundings. The Domestic Violence Project is a Washtenaw County agency dedicated to providing temporary shelter, counseling, and legal assistance to victims of domestic abuse. It also works to change cultural attitudes toward abuse through education and public awareness campaigns. The Domestic Violence Project once shared office space with Soundings and worked closely with Soundings within the Ann Arbor community. For example, Soundings and the Domestic Violence Project were part of a community effort to receive funding for a substance abuse program, "Primary Prevention Services for Women," and the two agencies proposed jointly to form the Women's Resource Consortium, as detailed in the Michigan Office of Substance Abuse Services file (Grants, Box 5, Soundings).
  - 1984 Annual Membership Meeting, September 1984 (Box 2)
    (includes 1983 meeting minutes)
  - 1989
    - January-March (Box 2)
    - April-June (Box 2)
    - July-September (Box 2)
    - Annual Meeting September 1989 (Box 2)
    - October-December (Box 2)
  - 1990
    - January-March (Box 2)
    - April-June (Box 2)
    - July-September (Box 2)
    - Annual Meeting September 1990 (Box 2)
    - October-December (Box 2)
  - 1991
    - January-March (Box 2)
    - April-June (Box 2)
    - July-September (Box 2)
    - Annual Meeting September 1991 (Box 2)
    - October-December (Box 2)
- Board of Directors
  The Board of Directors series (1.3 linear feet) is comprised mainly of board meeting minutes and other documents (agendas, memoranda, reports, correspondence) that made up the board member "packet" for each meeting. The series also contains early materials such as Soundings' articles of incorporation, bylaws, and Gerry Brown's notes from the first year of meetings. Other material includes budget and correspondence files, as well as files for various committees and a separate file of reports from the executive director (which duplicates reports in the annual minutes files). These files are arranged in the order in which they were accessioned.
  - Soundings Articles of Incorporation 1977-1978 (Box 3)
    (includes notes and clippings)
  - Soundings Bylaws 1977-1991 (Box 3)
  - Glenora Brown's Notes February 1978-December 1978 (Box 3)
  - Meetings: agendas, minutes, committee and executive director's reports, some correspondence
    - 1978-1979 (Box 3)
      (includes a schedule of meetings 1978-1983)
    - 1980 (Box 3)
    - 1981 (Box 3)
    - 1982 (Box 3)
    - 1983 (Box 3)
    - 1984 (Box 3)
    - 1985 (Box 3)
    - 1986 (Box 3)
    - 1987 (Box 3)
    - 1988 (Box 3)
    - 1989 (Box 3)
    - 1990 (Box 3)
    - 1991 (Box 3)
    - 1992 (Box 3)
    - 1993 (Box 3)
    - 1994 (Box 3)
  - Soundings Budgets 1979-1986 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence June 1984-December 1990 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1994-1995 (Box 3)
  - Board Member Packet circa 1991-1994 (Box 3)
  - Board of Directors Information (Box 3)
  - Background/Updates to Board 1992 (Box 3)
  - Board Retreat 1987-1993 (Box 3)
  - Advisory Council
    - Correspondence April 1978-April 1985 (Box 3)
    - Minutes and Administrative Materials November 1989-May 1992 (Box 3)
  - Executive Director's Reports September 1988-April 1993 (Box 3)
  - Staff Meeting Minutes October 1984-April 1995 (Box 3)
  - PR/Marketing Committee April 1994-February 1996 (Box 3)
  - Program Committee October 1992-November 1994 (Box 3)
  - Next Program Committee Meeting September 1993-August 1994 (Box 3)
  - Board Resource Development (Box 3)
- Grants and Fundraising
  The Grants and Fundraising series (1.2 linear feet) consists of grant applications, correspondence, announcements, and other materials pertaining to Soundings' fundraising activities. There are two types of files in this series: first, files on organizations (both government and private sector) from which Soundings sought financial assistance and second, those files having to do with various events which Soundings staged in order to raise money or increase its public profile. Some of the grant applications, such as the one submitted to the Michigan Office of Substance Abuse Services, were presented as a joint effort with other Washtenaw County social services agencies. The files are arranged in the order in which they were accessioned.
  - Englander's Tree Fundraiser 1991 (Box 4)
  - Domino's Christmas Celebration Request 1992 (Box 4)
  - Major Donor Thank You February 1991 (Box 4)
  - Women's Chamber Chorus November 1992-May 1993 (Box 4)
  - Chenille Sisters Benefit Concert May 1988-September 1988 (Box 4)
  - Ford Motor Company May 1992 (Box 4)
  - Society Bank 1991 (Box 4)
  - Soundings Breakfast Briefing June 1990 (Box 4)
  - Benefit, Art School, Gertrude Bleiberg 1990 (Box 4)
  - Ann Arbor Area Foundation
    (later known as the Ann Arbor Area Community Foundation)
    - 1979-1981 (Box 4)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 4)
    - 1987 (Box 4)
    - 1990 (Box 4)
  - Ann Arbor Area Community Foundation
    - 1991 (Box 4)
    - Volunteer Coordinator 1991 (Box 4)
    - 1992-1994 (Box 4)
    - Turning Points Grant 1990, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Women's Foundation 1994 (Box 4)
  - Private Industry Council
    - ECUS Standards (Box 4)
    - ECUS
      - 1984 (Box 4)
      - 1985-1986 (Box 4)
      - 1986-1987 (Box 4)
    - EDWAA 1991-1992 (Box 4)
  - Waltec Proposal December 1988 (Box 4)
  - US Department of Labor
    - CETA Proposal 1980 (Box 4)
    - Grant Proposal 1980 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Department of Labor
    - Displaced Homemakers Proposal 1980 (Box 4)
    - DHP Contracts 1981-1983 (Box 4)
      (Displaced Homemakers Program)
    - DHP Contracts 1985-1989 (Box 4)
    - Previous Proposals and Contract 1981 (Box 4)
    - Reports 1988-1989 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Office of Substance Abuse Services 1987 (Box 5)
  - Washtenaw United Way
    - 1978 (Box 5)
    - 1981 (Box 5)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 5)
    - 1983 (Box 5)
    - 1984 (Box 5)
    - 1985 (Box 5)
    - 1986 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence 1991-1994 (Box 5)
      (includes a 1991 grant proposal)
    - Campaign Designation Correspondence 1993-1995 (Box 5)
  - Community Development Block Grant (CDBG)
    - 1983 (Box 5)
    - 1986 (Box 5)
    - 1987 (Box 5)
    - 1988 (Box 5)
    - Quarterly Reports
      - 1987-1988 (Box 5)
      - 1988-1989 (Box 5)
      - 1989-1990 (Box 5)
    - Client Reports 1989-1990 (Box 5)
    - Contracts 1983-1989 (Box 5)
  - City of Ypsilanti 1988-1989 (Box 5)
  - Michigan Rehabilitative Services (MRS)
    - Supportive Counseling June 1988-July 1988 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence June 1988-June 1989 (Box 5)
- Financial
  The Financial series (0.5 linear feet) contains federal and state tax information and forms filed by Soundings from 1981 to 1994. In addition, this series includes statistics, audits, and financial reports.
  - Taxes
    - IRS
      - W2s and W3s 1981-1992 (Box 5)
      - Income Tax Return (Form 990)
        - 1977-1986 (Box 5)
        - 1987-1993 (Box 5)
      - Form 1096 1981-1987 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Annual Report, Nonprofit Corporations 1981-1995 (Box 5)
    - City of Ann Arbor, Personal Property Exemption 1990 (Box 5)
    - Backup of Cost Allocation Plan, CDBG 1991-1992 (Box 5)
  - Statistics 1984-1986 (Box 5)
  - Audits 1991-1995 (Box 5)
  - Financial Statements 1991-1994 (Box 5)
- Audiovisual
  The Audiovisual series (1 linear foot) is made up of four subseries: Sound Recordings, Videotapes, Photographs and Slides.
  - Sound Recordings
    The Sound Recordings subseries consists of audio cassettes. Most of these tapes are recordings of interviews with Soundings staff members, volunteers, and clients, which aired on local radio programs. In addition, there are promotional radio spots (both initial takes and the final cuts) created by Soundings, also for local broadcast. Musical audio recordings consist of a recording of a former client of Soundings, Bessie Leggett Phelan, singing the Soundings theme song, "Soundings," which she also composed, as well as the "Ode to Gerry," sung by some of the staff on the occasion of Soundings' tenth anniversary. There is also an audio 'letter' to Gerry Brown from the rest of the Soundings staff.
    - "Soundings": theme song, written and performed by Soundings alumna Bessie Phelan, 2 audiocassettes (Box 6)
      - Takes one and two (Box 6)
      - Take three (Box 6)
    - "To Ger from Gerri, Esther, Debbie, & Lynne": audio letter February 1987 (Box 6)
    - "An Ode to Gerry," December 10, 1986 (Box 6)
      (sung to the tune of "You Are My Sunshine" and recorded at Esther Donahue's house)
    - Women in Business, WCAR Radio 1090 AM: Interview with Soundings clinical director Joan Weiss, May 27, 1992 (Box 6)
    - "Soundings' Slide Show" (Box 6)
      (includes two takes; related to "Soundings Slide Show" in the Visual Materials subseries)
  - Videotapes
    The Videotapes sub-subseries, much like the Sound Recording subseries, includes interviews on public access cable television stations and promotional television spots. One of the taped interviews includes a live performance of "Soundings" by Bessie Phelan.
    - Education Up Close with Justine Bykowski, "Soundings!" Saline TV: interviews with executive director Lin Orrin, administrative assistant Amy Bennett, and volunteer coordinator Amy Bailey, January 29, 1992 (Box 6)
    - Access Ann Arbor, "Soundings," Community Access TV: interviews with clinical director Joan Weiss, volunteer Jennie Pittman, and former client Carol Miller, June 1992 (Box 6)
    - Soundings: A Center for Women: promotional video, September 3, 1992, 3 videotapes; one VHS format copy and two professional broadcast formats, including the original edit master (Box 6)
    - Access Ann Arbor, "Soundings," Community Access TV: interviews with volunteer director Terri Johnson, intern Kristen Blackburn, and Soundings graduate Bessie Phelan, August 1993 (Box 6)
    - Education Up Close with Justine Bykowski, "Soundings, Part 2," Saline TV: interview with volunteer coordinator Stephanie Barbee and volunteer Sarah Newland re: Divorce Kit Service, September 9, 1992 (Box 6)